let currentQuestionIndex = 0;//which question are you currently on
let correct;//storing the correct answer
let help;//storing the help tip
let questions = [];//storing the questions in the array
let correctANS = [];//storing the correct answer in the array
let selectedANS = [];//storing the selected answer in the array
let currentQuestion;//getting the current question that is displayed on the screen
//pushing the questions into the array
questions.push({ Question: "What school do we go to?", 
options: ["MTU", "ATU", "CIT", "LIT"], 
correct: "MTU", 
help : " It ends in a U" });//question options corrrect and help are objection inside the array storing different things 

questions.push({ Question: "What is the capital of Ireland", 
options: ["Dublin", "Tralee", "Cork", "Limerick"], 
correct: "Dublin", 
help: "Its where the Spire is" });

questions.push({ Question: "Who is the president of Ireland", 
options: ["Michael D. Higgins", "Sabina Coyne", "Leo Varadkar", "Mary Robinson"], 
correct: "Michael D. Higgins", 
help: "this person is also a poet" });

questions.push({ Question: "What year was Ireland founded", 
options: ["1937", "1899", "1921", "1915"], 
correct: "1921", 
help: "On this year Adolf Hitler became the FÃ¼hrer of the Nazi" });

questions.push({ Question: "What is Ireland's National dish", 
options: ["Mince pie", "Irish stew", "Ulster Fry", "Bacon and Cabbage"],
correct: "Irish stew", 
 help: "This meals ingredients mainly include potatoes and vegetables" });

questions.push({ Question: "Which currency is used in the Republic of Ireland?", 
options: ["Dollar", "Euro", "Pound", "Yen"], 
correct: "Euro", 
help: "it is used by majority of european countries" });

questions.push({ Question: "How many counties does ireland have?", 
options: ["22", "45", "32", "12"], 
correct: "32", 
help: "it has less counties than England" });

questions.push({ Question: "Which river flows through the centre of Dublin?", 
options: ["River Nile", "Ganji River", "The River Liffey", "the Poddle"], 
correct: "The River Liffey",
 help: "it ryhmes with giffy" });

questions.push({ Question: "Which song by Ed Sheeran mentions an Irish city?", 
options: ["Cork", "Malmo", "Mayo", "Galway"], 
correct: "Galway", 
help: "this place is home to The Burren" });

questions.push({ Question: "what is ireland's national animal?", 
options: ["Dog", "Whale", "Red deer", "Irish hare"], 
correct: "Irish hare", 
help: "this one is kinda obvious" });


//randomizing the questions by swapping the order of the questions 
function randomquestion(){
    for(let i = 0; i< 10; i++){
    let j = Math.floor(Math.random() * questions.length);//randomizing a number from one to the length of the array questions 
        if(j == currentQuestion){
        let temp = questions[i];
        questions[i] = questions[j];
        questions[j] = temp;
        }
}
}



//displaying the questions in the span tag area next to the radio button in the html for the quiz 
function displayQuestion() {
    currentQuestion  = questions[currentQuestionIndex];//getting the current question that is being displayed 
    document.getElementById("question").innerText = currentQuestion.Question;//outputting the question in the question section in the quiz html
    document.getElementById("labelA").innerText = currentQuestion.options[0];//outputing the options in the option area next to the radio button in the span tag area in the html
    document.getElementById("labelB").innerText = currentQuestion.options[1];
    document.getElementById("labelC").innerText = currentQuestion.options[2];
    document.getElementById("labelD").innerText = currentQuestion.options[3];
}


//no argument function to check when the next button has been clicked
document.getElementById("nextQuestionButton").addEventListener("click", function () {
    randomquestion();
 // Check if there are more questions
    if (currentQuestionIndex < 4) {
        currentQuestionIndex++;
        displayQuestion();//display the question if there still more questions 
        correctANS.push(currentQuestion.correct);//pushes the correct answer into the array for corret answers 
        localStorage.setItem("questions", JSON.stringify(questions));//stores the question shown into local storage
    } else {
        //when the questions are done make the nextbutton dissapear and the finish button appear 
            document.getElementById("nextQuestionButton").style.display = "none";
            document.getElementById("finish").style.display = "block";
    }
    let Checked = document.querySelector('[name="answer"]:checked');//checking what radio button has been clicked
    let selectedText = Checked.parentElement.innerText;//getting the text from the which radio button has been clicked 
    if (Checked) {
        selectedANS.push(selectedText);//pushing the text from the selected answer into the selected answer array
        console.log("Answer: " + selectedANS);
        console.log("Correct Answers:", correctANS);
    }
    let score = 0;
    let percScore;
    for(let i = 0; i < 5; i++){
        //checking if the selected answer is equal to the correct answer 
        if(selectedANS[selectedText] === correctANS[currentQuestion.correct]){
            score++;
        }
    }
    percScore = (score / 5) * 100//getting the percentage of the users score 
    localStorage.setItem("Score", JSON.stringify(percScore));//storing the users score using local storage 
    localStorage.setItem("Answer", JSON.stringify(selectedANS));//storing the users answer using local storage 
    console.log("Score:", percScore);
    progressBar();//calls the progress bar function everytime the next button is clicked 
});



//displaying the progress bar with the correct numbers 
function progressBar(){
    let bar = document.getElementById("progress bar");
    bar.innerHTML = `${currentQuestionIndex+1}`+ `/`+ `${5}`;
}


//putting the tips in for the user using mouseover and mouseout 
function Tips(){
    let tip = document.getElementById("Tip");
    tip.innerHTML = `${currentQuestion.help}`;
    document.getElementById("Tip").addEventListener("mouseout", function(){
        tip.innerHTML = "Tip";

    });
}

//using a no argument function to check if the finish button has been clicked then using window.open to open the summary window
document.getElementById("finish").addEventListener("click", function (){
    let summary = window.open("summary.html", "Summary", "width=450,height=650");
    summary;
})

displayQuestion();
progressBar();
